<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caveat for subjects, moderating the Observator. Wherein his chiefest arguments are confuted, the Kings iust prerogative manitained [sic]: and the priviledge of the subiect no wayes preiudiced: by William Ball, Gent.</title>
            <author>Ball, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E118_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860651</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860651</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112776</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112776)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E118[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caveat for subjects, moderating the Observator. Wherein his chiefest arguments are confuted, the Kings iust prerogative manitained [sic]: and the priviledge of the subiect no wayes preiudiced: by William Ball, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Ball, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Parker, Henry.  Observations upon some of his Majesties late answers and expresses.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 19th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112776:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT FOR SVBJECTS, Moderating the Obſervator. WHEREIN His chiefeſt Arguments are confuted, the Kings iuſt Prerogative manitained: and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Subiect no wayes Preiudiced:</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Ball,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Printed at London 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112776:2"/>
            <head>A Caveat for Subiects.</head>
            <p>IT is uſuall (I know) for Bookes to have Prefaces, and Playes Prologues; but whoſoever peruſeth this, muſt expect nothing but conciſe reaſons; foraſmuch as <hi>Vnuſquiſque ſuo ſenſu abundat,</hi> ſo let him reflect and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of this at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator, pag. 1. ſaith, <hi>That power is originally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in the people, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the anſwer is, that power is in God <hi>primario &amp; per ſe,</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle; <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and in the King or people, but only <hi>ſecundario &amp; derivative;</hi> Power or dominion is not a gift of Nature, that is to ſay, naturally inherent in us: for if it were, then might all men have equal power, for that by nature we are all equall; but power is a gift of God to Nature, and is <hi>gratia gratis data;</hi> and yet power is congruous in nature, as was the power of King, and office of Prieſthood in <hi>Melchiſedec:</hi> for ſurely he had them both given, or appointed to him by God, being by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation <hi>King of Righteouſnes and King of Peace, Heb.</hi> 2.7. And therefore it is not likely that he uſurped to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Regall title of King, no more then he did of being Prieſt; and yet it is very probable, that it was alſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Reaſon and Nature, that although not tyrannicall, yet peaceable Kingly reigne, and ſacred Prieſthood did fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong to him: for he is by moſt Divines thought to have been <hi>Sem</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Noah:</hi> and by the law of Nature, of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of moſt Nations, the eldeſt is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112776:2"/>ſo that what was the right of <hi>Adam, Seth,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seth and his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt to cal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord, that is to ſay, to give to God ſome ſet forme of worſhip as prieſts did, &amp;c.</note> might belong unto him by birth-right, although it may be God confirmed it unto him extraordinarily. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, power or dominion is derived from God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous in Nature: but the power is in the people onely when they are abſolutely free to chuſe to themſelves what forme of government they pleaſe, as were the Iewes before they ſubiected themſelves to Kings, being formerly freed from the bondage of Egypt by the ſinger of God. The Romanes when they erected their Senate and Conſuls, having rebelliouſly (for it was no better) ſhaken off the yoke of Kings. The Venetians, when they firſt inſtituted their Common-wealth. But in Monarchies, where the people have been brought into ſubiection either by the ſword, as in Turky, Perſia, and the like; or by innate, and preſcribing, and prevalent authority, as in Florence, or by both, as in France and Caſtile; in theſe Dominions power is not inherent in the people, but in the Prince. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome hereditary Monarkes are more limited then others, as is the King of France more then the great Turk, and the King of England more then the King of France: yet is their power derived immediately from God, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in themſelves, not in the people: for thoſe limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are (in conquered Nations) but mere donatives of grace proceeding from the Prince or his ſucceſſors to the people, touching certaine immunities and priviledges; ſo that the Prince his power is the efficient cauſe of them, and ſuch immunities or priviledges are but as materiall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Now as it is moſt improper to ſay, that the effect ſhould cauſe its owne cauſe, ſo is it to ſay, that a priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged people ſhould cauſe the Princes power, or that <hi>Power ſhould remain originally in ſuch a priviledged people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112776:3"/>
Some Nations elect their Rings, or Princes, and reſtrain them farre more by conditionall inaugurations, then he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Monarkes are, or ought to bee reſtrained or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited. Yet have not ſuch Nations power in themſelves totally, but onely partially; that is, they have power to conditionare with their Kings or Princes, how farre forth they will be ſubiect, and by what Rules they will bee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned; but they have not power to conditionate with their Kings or Princes, that they will only bee ſubiect at their owne pleaſures, and as themſelves ſhall thinke good; that is to ſay, if they pleaſe at any time, to aſſume more liberty unto themſelves, and to alter and diſanull former Conſtitutions of Government, they may doe it without the conſent of their Kings, or Princes. This they cannot doe without treaſon to their Crownes or Diadems: For although the perſons of ſuch Princes bee elective, yet is their power permanent, <hi>jure conſtituto Coronae;</hi> which though they claime not as from progenitor, yet are they inveſted therewith as from predeceſſors. And therefore being enthroned, they enioy their dignities by preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that is to ſay, what belonged to their predeceſſors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth in the ſame manner to them, being once inveſted; nor can ſuch Nations revolt from their elected princes, without being reputed rebels.</p>
            <p>Now of this nature are the Kings of Poland, Hungary, and ſome other (to ſpeake nothing of the Duke of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, for hee is meerely titulary, and a cypher) and ſuch Kings firſt and principally claime their authority from God, the authour of all power, who enſpheareth them in the Orb of dignity above others.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, they acknowledge it from the generall conſent of the Nation which made choyce of them, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112776:3"/>over which they rule. And ſurely ſuch was the right and title of <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of Iſrael: for hee was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, 1 Sam. Chap. 9. verſ. 17. then annointed by <hi>Samuel,</hi> chap. 10. verſ. 1. afterwards approved by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>ibid.</hi> verſ. 24. And finally, confirmed in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Chap. 11. verſ. 14. And in the ſame manner was <hi>David</hi> likewiſe eſtabliſhed in his Kingdome; ſo that their firſt and chiefeſt claime was immediately from God, and their ſecond from the conſent of the people. Nor is it of any conſequence to alledge, as the Obſervator ſeemeth to inferre, page 1. that thoſe Kings had an extraordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution from God; and therefore they might more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully claime their right, as appointed, and appropriated to them by God. For to ſuch Allegation it will bee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That <hi>there is no power but of God,</hi> Rom. 13. So that whether God inſtitute Kings by extraordinary, or ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanes, it maketh no matter. For although <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were inſtituted extraordinarily by Gods ſpeciall appointment; yet moſt of the Kings of Iudah and Iſrael reigned after them but by ordinary ſucceſſion; had they not therefore the ſame power that <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had? Surely the Scriptures tell us they had. The Prieſts and Prophets in the old Law had an extraordinary vocation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecialy the Prophets: the Prieſts or Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel have but an ordinary vocation, are they therefore defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in power to thoſe of the old Law? Or have they not their vocation from God, becauſe they have not extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary calling? Surly no. For how could Sacraments be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, &amp; the word preached? So it is with Monarkes: for though they have but ordinary ſucceſſion; yet is their power immediatly from God. Our Soveraigne is a free
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112776:4"/>(though in ſome things a limited) Monarch, and deriveth therefore his power immediatly (not mediatly as do other inferior miniſters of iuſtice) from God. And as touching limitations and priviledges, they are nothing elſe as (afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) but acts of grace conferred on this Nation by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties predeceſſors in ſeverall ages, and at ſeverall times, and ſome of them lately by his Maieſty himſelfe, as the continuation of this preſent Parliament, the aboliſhing of the Star-chamber and high Commiſſion cenſures, and the like. But theſe priviledges, and others granted to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, diſ-inveſt the King of no primary or Birth-right-roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, but only oblige him in honour to obſerve them as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants. A Lord purchaſeth a Mannor for himſelf and his Heires for ever; his ſon and ſucceſſors grant certain Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes to the tenants, and oblige their heires for ever to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them: ſo the tenants live in a more free ſtate and condition then they did in the firſt purchaſers dayes, and paying their rents, and performing their ſervices, they are not altogeher ſubiect to bee turned out at the pleaſure (or rather diſpleaſure) of the Lord: but doth this Franchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or freedome of theirs, cauſe the Lord to derive his right or title from his tenants? Law and experience tell us no. And this is our Soveraignes caſe; The conquerour by his ſword, or by deed of gift, or rather indeed by both, came in as a Purchaſer of the Kingdome of England for himſelf and his heires for ever, and by the law of Conqueſt had power to have made greater alteration in the State then he did; and to have induced what forme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had thought good, even as the King of Spain hath done in <hi>Navarre</hi> and the <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> yet hee did not, but only impoſed ſome hard things, as the having of Lawes in the French tongue, which the people generally underſtood
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112776:4"/>not, Cover-few-bell, and the like, his ſucceſſors ofterwards did immune and eaſe the people from ſuch grievances, ſo that they lived, and live at more liberty, and enioy more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely their liberties and properties: But doe therefore ſuch immunities granted to the people, cauſe the King to derive his power and right from the people? The lawes and cuſtomes of all Nations and Kingdomes that live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Monarkes, tell us no. The ancient and preſent Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies of the world being ſufficient witneſſes therof, beſides the <hi>Dictamen</hi> of Scripture and reaſon already inſerted.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator pag. 2. ſaith, that it is an errour in ſome Princes, <hi>to ſtrive more to bee great over their people, then in their people.</hi> It may be ſome Princes have committed ſuch an errour; but withall let the obſervator take notice, that it is convenient for a free Prince to be both, that is to ſay, to have them wealthy, and yet obedient ſubiects: for if he be only great in his people, and not over them, hee may reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the now Roman or German Emperour, or the ancient Kings of France, the one whereof is daily in danger to bee diſ-inveſted by commotion and combinations of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the other were heretofore almoſt continually mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by factions of their Peeres and people; and ſurely, the French themſelves have greatly occaſioned the heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of divers tributes &amp; impoſitions which they undergo: for they ever and anon riſing in Armes againſt their King, gave him occaſion to ſlave them the more, by his reconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them, or reducing them into his obedience, ſo that had they ſubſiſted in due allegeance, 'tis likely their King had been as equally <hi>great over as in them;</hi> which equality or parity in government, is (no doubt) the moſt happy and bleſſed co union that any Prince and people can enioy.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator telleth us in the ſame page, that the King
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112776:5"/>though he be <hi>ſingulis major,</hi> yet he is <hi>univerſis minor.</hi> But why ſo? The Head Naturall is not onely <hi>ſingulis,</hi> but alſo <hi>univerſis membris major Dignitate</hi> (though it may 'tis not ſo <hi>in univerſis,</hi> as ſhall be by and by declared) For the Head hath in it ſelfe all Sences, other Members receive from it, but Feeling onely, and Motion; the Head governeth and directeth the whole Body, and is therefore in dignitie more Noble then all the Members of the Body conſidered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and yet though it be more noble and excellent then them all (for as much as Motion and Feeling dimane from the Braine which is in the Head to them all) notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>in univerſis,</hi> in all things, or Faculties, the Head is not more excellent then all the Members; for the Heart is the Seat of Life (according to moſt Philoſophers (being <hi>primum vivens, &amp; ultimum moriens,</hi> and from it proceedeth naturall heat; the Stomack likewiſe adminiſtreth ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and aliment; the Feet goe, and the Hands worke, and without them the Head cannot ſubſiſt, yet are they all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to the Head: and even ſo is it, or ought it to be in the Body Politick, unleſſe we muſt beleeve the Obſervator, who in his 19. Page ſayth, That <hi>the Head Politicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives more ſubſiſtence from the Body then it gives, &amp;c.</hi> But by his leave, if Priviledges and Immunities are (as they are) matters of Grace, proceeding from free Monarchs (for of ſuch the Treatiſe is) to the People, doe not ſuch Heads give as much ſubſiſtence to the Body Politick, as they receive from it? The Obſervator telleth us, <hi>Page</hi> 6. That <hi>Edward the Firſt was the firſt</hi> (whether he were, or no, it is not materiall) <hi>that repaired the Breaches which the Conqueſt had made upon this Nation:</hi> if ſo, did not hee, by ſuch his reparation, give as much ſubſiſtence to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, as he received from the Common-wealth, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112776:5"/>Body Politick? And doe not his Succeſſors give likewiſe as much as they receive, when they conferre the like acts of Grace? Surely, he that conſidereth rightly <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and all other Priviledges and Immunities, which now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the free-borne People of this Kingdome, will finde them firſt to have proceeded from the Grace and Grant of our Kings: and therefore it is improper to ſay, That <hi>the Head Politick doth not give as much ſubſiſtence to the Body Politick, as it receives from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Obſervator ſayth likewiſe in his ſecond Page, That <hi>id quod efficit tale, eſt magis tale;</hi> meaning thereby, that the People conferring, as the efficient Cauſe, Power on the King, have ioyntly more Power in themſelves.</p>
            <p>It hath beene ſhewed alreadie, that free Monarchs, ſuch as our King is, derive not their Power from the People, but immediately from God: But ſuppoſe, our King did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarily acknowledge his Power from this Nations gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent; as it may be, doth the King of <hi>Poland</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his Power in part from the Ariſtocracie of that Kingdome; and as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> did in part from the <hi>Iewes</hi> approbation and conſent: notwithſtanding it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes not from hence, that the People are the ſole efficient Cauſe of the Kings Power, but onely the ſecundarie and partiall. Now, when it is ſaid, that <hi>id quod efficit tale, eſt magis tale,</hi> it is to be underſtood of entire and totall cauſes; but in this caſe, the People being at the moſt but the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall cauſe of the Kings Power, the Axiome of Rule faileth: as for example, the Moone being of her ſelfe a Body darke, receives her Light (at leaſt wiſe her chiefeſt) from the Sunne, as from an entire cauſe; the Sunne is therefore truly ſayd to be more Light, being the totall ſubordinate cauſe of Light; in this caſe therefore it is truly ſayd, <hi>id quod ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112776:6"/>tale, eſt magis tale:</hi> but the Sunne, <hi>mediante homine; producit hominem; &amp; mediante Leone, Leonem; &amp; mediante Planta, Plantam;</hi> for that the Sunne affordeth to all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and vegitable creatures an influx of vigour and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat: yet for as much as the Sunne is, in the production of theſe creatures, but a partiall and not an integrall cauſe; it were abſured to ſay, that the Sunne were more a man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then is a man; or more a Lyon, then is a Lyon; or more a Plant, then is a Plant: and ſo is it to ſay, that becauſe a King may acknowledge his Power in part received from the Peoples generall conſent, that therefore the People have more Power then himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator telleth us, <hi>Page</hi> 3. That <hi>the Kings dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was erected to preſerve the Communalty, the Communalty was not created for his ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſomewhat too harſh, eſpecially if wee conſider our King to be, <hi>in all Cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Civill, next and immediately under Chriſt, ſupreme Head and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour:</hi> ſuch words would have beene better accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to a Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> then to a King of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Iewes,</hi> I beleeve, when they asked a King at Gods hands, were ſomewhat inclining to the Obſervators opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for they deſired a King for their owne ends, chiefely to Iudge them, and to fight their Battailes; not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that if they had a King, hee muſt and ought to have a Kingly Dominion over them: Whereupon God cauſed the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> to inſtruct them concerning the Praeeminence of a King; and, that if they would have a King, a King would be ſuch, and ſuch a man, as is evidently characterized in the firſt of <hi>Samuel, chap.</hi> 8. where, amongſt other things, <hi>verſe</hi> 17. the Prophet ſayth,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112776:6"/>
               <hi>Hee will take the Tenth of your Sheepe, and yee ſhall be his ſervants:</hi> Where, by the word <hi>will,</hi> hee ſheweth the Authoritie which Kings would have; and by the word <hi>ſhall,</hi> hee ſheweth the Obedience that ſubiects ſhould have: nor did the Prophet ſpeake of ſome, or to ſome few onely; but of all, and to all the people (at leaſt-wiſe to all the chiefeſt of them) ſaying, <hi>Yee ſhall be his ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire therefore, that the Obſervator and all his other adhaerents, would take more ſpeciall notice of this Text of the Prophet, and that of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> confirmation of this Text, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher Power:</hi> For, though Chriſtian Monarchs ought not, by the Rules of Chriſtianitie, to Tyrannize, nor make our Sonnes their Slaves, or our Daughters their Concubines, and the like; as did many of the Kings of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> yet ought they not to be thought ſo contemptible, as that the Communaltie was no way created for their ſervice.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator ſayth in the ſame Page, <hi>That the right of Conqueſt cannot be pleaded, to acquit Princes of that which is due to the people, as the authors and ends of all Power; for meere Force cannot alter the courſe of Nature, and fruſtrate Law; and if it could, there were more reaſon why the people might iuſtifie Force to regaine due libertie, then the Prince might to ſubvert the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Obſervators leave, for his firſt Clauſe it is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alreadie, That in Monarchies the people are not the authors or ends of Power: for the ſecond Clauſe, That <hi>meere Force cannot alter the courſe of Nature, or fruſtrate the tonour of Law;</hi> that is to ſay, that meere Force
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112776:7"/>cannot captivate and debaſe a people by nature free, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under a law of common conſent. I ſuppoſe the words, <hi>cannot alter,</hi> ſhould have been, <hi>cannot, de jure, alter, or ought not to alter,</hi> &amp;c. For that force can alter, and <hi>de facto</hi> hath altered the freedom and lawes of people and nations, is known to moſt men, Hiſtories and Chronicles teſtifying to the world, the ſeveral alterations &amp; forms of government which conquerors have induced; but whether they ought ſo to have done, is a queſtion; yet ſhould the <hi>Obſervator</hi> and his adherents take advice, that though in Nature there is a parity of mankind, and therefore dominion may not ſeeme to be intended by nature, yet God the authour of Nature, foreſeeing the fall of man, and the depravation in nature, which did enſue thereof, intended power and dominion, and that ſome ſhould bee maſters and or hers ſervants; ſome command, and others obey; ſome ſhould become ſlaves to tyrants, others ſubiects to free Monarks; others members of popular Eſtates: and theſe things God hath ordained by his divine wiſedome, according to his will, and diſpoſes and alters them at his pleaſure: <hi>But as for the pot, it aught not to ſay to the Potter, Why haſt thou made mee thus?</hi> It is enough for it to know, that there is no power but of God, and ſo to be appliable to the uſe it was made for; if for hononr, to honour; if for ſervility, to ſervility, being ſubiect <hi>for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, Rom</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>Of a ſtrange nature therefore are thoſe words, viz. <hi>There were more reaſon why the people might juſtifie force to regaine due liberty, then the Prince might to ſubvert the ſame.</hi> If this doctrine had been good, our Saviour would ſurely have counſelled the Iewes (when they asked him whether it were lawfull to give tribute to Caeſar) to have kept their money in their purſes, or to have made up a ſtock of it, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112776:7"/>by force to have ſought to regaine their due liberty from Caeſar, and not have bid them, <hi>Give unto Ceſar what is Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars.</hi> If it be alledged, that in caſe Chriſt had counſelled the Iewes ſo, they would have plaid the Iewes inceed, and have accuſed him of high treaſon; What then? would Chriſt have concealed, or did he at any time conceale the truth for ſeare of the Iewes accuſations? When hee was coniured to expreſſe whether or no hee were the Sonne of God (a thing more hatefull to the Iewes eares, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of tribute could have beene to the eares of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans) Chriſt anſwered, <hi>Thou haſt ſaid it,</hi> which is as much as <hi>Yes.</hi> But ſuppoſe the Iewes would have accuſed him of high treaſon, in caſe hee had denied tribute to Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, and that God would not have ſuch a vile imputation as treaſon laid on the redeemer of the world. Yet had regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of due liberty by force been lawfull, Chriſtmight have ſaid, <hi>Ye may give tribute to Ceſar</hi> in the potentiall Mood (in which words no exception could have been taken) and not have ſaid, give tribute to Ceſar, or <hi>give unto Ceſar what is Ceſars,</hi> in the imperative mood. Or otherwiſe, when they asked him, whether it were lawful to pay tribute to Ceſar, he might only have anſwered them, <hi>Yes;</hi> but foreſeeing in his divine wiſedome, that ſome indirect conſtructions might be made of ſuch a ſingle word, as <hi>Yes,</hi> tis lawfull to pay it, yee may pay it if yee pleaſe; tis not againſt the law of God, if ye doe pay it, &amp;c. therefore Chriſt bid them ſhew him a peece of money, and bid them <hi>give it unto Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> informing the covetous minds of that perverſe people, that they ought and were obliged to part with their money and ſubſtance to Ceſar if demanded as a tribute; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let Arguments of Divinity paſſe, and to induce a few State reaſons: If <hi>the people may juſtify force to regaine due liberty,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112776:8"/>what Monarchy? what Ariſtocracy? what Popular eſtate can remain ſecure? the French ſubiects being in generall oppreſſed with taxes, may revolt from their King, if this <hi>Tenet</hi> be good; and ſo may the Spaniſh: the Poliſh Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants may rebell againſt the King and their Lords, for that they hold them in villinage: and the Townſmen and Boores in Holland, and the Piſani in Venice againſt the States, for their impoſing on them terrible excizes. This <hi>Tenet,</hi> or Poſition, may quadrate, it may bee with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh rebels (for they pretend by force to regaine due liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) but never with loyall ſubiects. And ſurely this <hi>Tenet</hi> or Poſition aforeſaid, is dangerous to all the Monarchies and States of the world, I even to Parliaments themſelves, if rightly conſidered, and oppoſite alſo to the law of God &amp; Nations. The Obſervator telleth us, p. 13. that <hi>where the people by publick authority will ſeek an inocnvenience to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the King is not ſo much intereſted as themſelves, it is more inconvenience to deny it, then grant it.</hi> This is a ſtrange aſſertion, and againſt all rule of Monarchicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Suppoſe (for a ſuppoſition is no fallaſie) that a Chriſtian people ſhould generally (which God forbid) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to revolt from Chriſtianity to Mahometaniſme; ſhould their King grant it? they ſeeme to bee more intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then the King, becauſe it concernes their ſalvation or damnation, is it iniuſtice therefore to deny it? Surely no; but moſt iuſt and acceptable to God to hinder them from it. Suppoſe this nation ſhould in generall (wich God of his goodnes prohibit) deſire to turn Anabaptiſt &amp; Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, whereof there are to many already, is the King bound, or ought he to condeſcend to their deſires? Surely no: but as Gods Vice gerent to oppoſe ſuch exorbitant inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people: but if the Aſſertion of the Obſervator
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112776:8"/>be good, <hi>Pilat</hi> ſeems to be excuſable whom the Obſervator condemneth in the page befoere: for the Iewes ſought by authority of the Prieſts &amp; Elders to crucifie Chriſt, (an inconvenience enough to themſelves) and inſtanced a law, <hi>and that by that law he ought to die, Ioh</hi> 1 9.7. and the Iewes were more intereſted in Chriſt, (he being their Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſubiect to their lawes, as they conceived) then was <hi>Pilate:</hi> ſo that according to this aſſertion of the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>it was more inconvenience and injuſtice for</hi> Pilate <hi>to have denied to the Iews</hi> Chriſt <hi>to have been crucified, then to have granted it.</hi> Iudica Deus.</p>
            <p>The Obſervator ſaith, pag. 17. <hi>The name of a King is great, I confeſſe, and worthy of great honour, but is not the name of a people greater?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Obſervator muſt give me leave to tell him, that in Monarchies where there were or are Kings, the name of a people neither was nor is greater then the name of a King; <hi>Senatus populuſque Romanus,</hi> ceaſed to be, and gave place to the name of <hi>Ceſar:</hi> The <hi>Ottoman</hi> name at this day, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies that great Empire ſubiect to that family; and ſo doth the name of <hi>Sophy</hi> the Perſian. The name of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> decorates their dominions; and ſo doth that of <hi>Burbon</hi> France. And I ſee no reaſon but why the name of <hi>Stewart</hi> ſhould doe as much in England. If it bee asked, But what availeth the names of theſe great Monarchs, without their Kingdomes or Dominions? The anſwer is, that Dominions are to Monarchs, as it were, material ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; themſelves (from whom their names reſult) as Formes. Now as the Forme is more worthy then its mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo is a free Monarch more worthy then his Empire, in reſpect of dignity politicall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112776:9"/>
And indeed the word Monarch infers as much for Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and is derived from <hi>Monarch,</hi> not Monarch from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. But it may bee ſome will inſtance from hence, that if it be ſo, the good of a Monarch ſeems to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the good of all his ſubiects in generall, ſo that a whole Kingdom or Empire ſhould be utterly pillaged, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and conſumed, rather then his treaſures bee deſtroyed. Not ſo: for though Empires &amp; Kingdoms are but as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall ſubiects, and Monarchs as forms politicall, yet even as in nature, formes cannot ſubſiſt without matter, (from whoſe power all formes, except the rationall ſoule, are edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) ſo in policy, Monarchy cannot ſubſiſt without their people, from whoſe ſubiection &amp; obedience their power is educed immediatly from God, as are formes from matter by nature: the good of both therefore muſt bee conſiſtent together, ſo that not <hi>ſalus populi</hi> alone; as the <hi>Obſervator</hi> would have it. but <hi>ſalus Regis &amp; populi,</hi> is the true end of Monarchicall government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus have I briefly anſwered the Obſervators chiefe arguments, from whence all his other aſſertions and concluſions are drawne, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him and all others, rather to ſtudy how to produce reaſons for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (where it is due) to Monarchs, then to derogate from Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall government to endeavour how to incline, &amp; not to diſaffect (by nice poſitions) the distracted mindes of the people towards the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to propound prudent Arguments which might move the King to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate with his Parliament and not by leſſening his authority, to divert him from it. Finally to ſeeke how to unite the King and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth &amp; not to diſunite them by impertinent and invalid conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. God of his goodnes grant co-union as much as in this world may be, between our Soveraigne and his people, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may know truly how to rule, and they to obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
